[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
welcome to the stoa everyone the store
is a place for us
to cohere in dialogue at the knife's
edge
of what matters most at this very moment
i'm nick benjamin
your host for this fourth and final
session incense
maker in residence zack stein who has so
far presented to us has met a
psychological framework
on shedding light on the psyche and
today we're going into an extended q a
unless zach has something else that he
wants to present to us
we'll jump right in with questions so
please write your questions in the chat
and unmute yourself when i call on you
to ask a question
given that this is being recorded and
put on youtube
if you want me to ask your question
before you please say so in the chat
welcome zach for this final session
thanks man my
uh my computer died over the weekend
so you're giving me a little bit lower
quality audio individual
there's like 100 chromebook here
which is actually doing surprisingly
well it makes me
question buying an expensive computer at
all
so happy to be here and uh i have
jerry rigged some headphones i don't
know mike here so if my
audio gets a little weird or i break up
let
me know zac your audio is quite
bad i'm happy to jump into questions
that with plan and questions about the
model are welcome but also
uh anything that you think the model
could be used to illuminate
it's quite bad is that okay uh it might
be good
um if you maybe turn your video off is
that better
is it that i'm breaking up or is that
the audio is too weak
the audio is fairly slow zach
but it might that might be better it
seems better
somewhat better now that the video is
off okay so the signal is too weak
is that better i did a couple meetings
before
yeah well so i'll i guess this is better
guys
yeah this this sounds better zach i can
start us off with the question
um okay let's let's try to do that and
if this doesn't work then i could
great so okay um
how do you see the family playing a role
in installment practices
uh the family is in fact perhaps the
primary
place where ensome and dynamics
happen um so
you know first place i go there is
some of the kind of cosmology let's say
from
religious traditions like tibetan
buddhism because there's a sense of like
why was one born into a particular
family
rather than another family right this
question of like
you don't choose your parents is what it
feels like
and sometimes there's this question of
like how did i get stuck with this
family
or thank god i got this family
so this this basic notion of that the
very first
environment the soul
is drawn into is the womb of
a particular woman uh
and so you know tibetan buddhism there's
that notion of like well no
you do choose your parents like you are
in the bardo realm
and you are trying to position yourself
into a particular condition of insolvent
for the next round right so you can
believe that or not and it's a
complex actually ontology required
to uh to make that work but
the the basic notion or the intuition
there the image
resonates right there is this sense that
the
the family is the is the primary effect
um and yet you don't choose it you know
abraham maslow used to talk about
uh you know there's the realm of
deficiency which is like the lower
levels and then there's this realm of
being so there's like
in the realm of being beyond self
actualization into self
transcendence in the being realm there's
like being values
and there's also things like being
injustice which is to say things that
appear to be unfair
just by virtue of the nature of reality
so like sometimes it feels this way when
you're born into a particular family
right uh like when uh
when a child um is born into
you know unbelievable poverty and
uh conditions of oppression and abuse
there's this question of like well you
know in some sense that's a social
injustice because of the economic system
and other dynamics but there's another
way in which
you know that soul landed in that family
and how what to make of that so this is
a very deep question
so the first answer is that is that the
in the early years of your life
the main theater in which installment
takes place as the family
and then most of the primary images
of self so you have to think about the
image of self as kind of like a
schema in a piagetian sense where
there's like
it places you in relation to other
people who are modeled a certain way in
relation to the world which is modeled a
certain way so there's this image this
deep image and the imagination
pre-conscious usually of the cell
and uh those first images of the self
emerge
from the family system very directly
and those primary images of stuff which
emerge in the early years
are the things that linger on
and structure the rest of the downscreen
downstream
schemas so this is a pretty classic
way of thinking about it so i think
something like that is also true that
even after you have left your family
let's say your family of origin and
you know you're a grown person and
you've worked with
trauma you've inherited and you've you
know deconstructed all the
simple notions uh that you were given
around the dinner table and all these
things
the family is still in there as a deep
rooted
often pre-conscious image of self
so what that means is usually there's a
way
that one goes from being brought into a
family
let's say without choosing it to then
choosing to create
new forms of family
so that's the that's the other dynamic
to note here is that
there's the conditions of insolent which
are not up to you
and then there are the conditions of
installment which you create
through action right so when you turn
the whole loop
and you move through the transcendent
and through choice you can
be in a situation where you actually are
making choices that affect the condition
of your installment and one of those
choices is things like
marriage children the other dynamics
that draw you into
deep interpersonal relationship and as i
was saying last time in the
question about polyamory like
commitments
to others until you die
like all in for this life
uh these are very real commitments that
humans have
i mean this is this is as real as like
gravity
in terms of the nature that the the the
the way the mind must adapt to the
immovable reality
of those kinds of social commitments
that you love i.e family
and so so that's just that the more
intense you can create the sense of
family and it doesn't need to be in like
a a simple
kind of capitalist atomic family sense
and it doesn't need to be in like a
ethnocentric like it's the family like
the italian mob
but this notion of like action
deep connection uh which through your
choice
eventually as you mature you create the
conditions of your installment
by creating the family and then of
course if the family involves having
children
then you're also creating the conditions
for the installment of the child who
comes into that family
um and uh so yeah so family is a root
and in fact when you look at uh john
rawls's work
is uh um
uh the fiercest of uh social justice
that i did my dissertation work on
brilliant social theorist he places uh
education schooling everything to do
with that dynamic
uh in family he basically says like you
know there's
the state there's the market and there's
the family something like that
and within the family is all of the
dynamics of intergenerational
transmission
um so in a sense you can extend the
notion of family beyond
even the blood connection
and even the small locality and you can
start thinking about
the human family or the
community as a family so the more that
the social system and the civilization
itself
has large pockets of that familial
soul root connection
then the more education becomes
education becomes a very rich dynamic
um as opposed to a superficial
institutionalized dynamic
uh so yeah so there's i think a lot to
say there you opened a kind of a
pretty big door maybe like a double door
when you ask about the family
and and insult and it's no coincidence
that
when you look at psychology and
especially depth psychology
you end up thinking a ton about the
family developmental psychology
similar bronfenbrenner et cetera so
excellent thank you we'll move on we can
deepen that line
with the family or we can totally change
course so i'm in your hands
how's the audio though is it coming
through okay audio is perfect
okay excellent so we'll jump to a
question from engine
hey zach um i'm not sure if i'm doing
the practicum
properly but my question is how could
like perfectionism
and procrastination um be better
understood
and potentially helped from eating a
metapsych lens
awesome yeah so this is exactly the kind
of practical
question because i've not asked myself
that question
about the metapsychology so this is me
improvising with the tools of the
metapsychology
trying to handle a very common
psychological
uh dynamic uh
and so you mentioned perfectionism and
procrastination so i'm gonna ask you a
couple questions
just make sure i'm answering your
question well so you so you're
tying procrastination and perfectionism
together
because there are definitely people who
are non-perfectionists who also
procrastinate
so you're looking at a particular kind
of procrastination so maybe you could
say
more about that
i think they're tied together in my life
um i don't think you need to answer it
it's very
specifically to that
but i'd be happy to the more specific we
get the more it actually is a real
thing and not a theoretical exercise
so if you don't want to be the focus of
attention i can certainly take it to the
abstract
but if you want to describe a situation
maybe
in your lived experience where this
dynamic shows up
and then we can kind of dig in
it's a silly example good most
most of the psyche is actually pretty
silly
like i basically just run my life by
what's urgent um i feel like
i used to joke in school oh if stuff
didn't have deadlines like nothing would
get done
and in the real world i i work for
myself and like [ __ ] there's no
deadlines
and so it's kind of manufacturing crises
and just
focusing on what's urgent so i thought
there's this great need
to have some sort of to-do list or
something like that
such that you could actually work on
what's important but not necessarily
urgent
but it's been literally like six months
and i still have not picked a to-do list
because it seems like such a
an important thing and i'm notoriously
picky or finicky when it comes to this
and so like i've read like
so many reviews and learned what's the
best and read all of this and every time
i have to pick it i just kind of put it
off
all right
yeah totally um so
a few things i'll mention here so
i think i saw a lot of heads nodding my
head my head was nodding
like a lot of people are now in
uh you know
not traditionally institution
institutionalized or completely
non-institutionalized work contexts
all right so that's worth noting and
most of us weren't prepared for that
because we went to these really
complicated institutions that were
pretty well run which were called
schools
so we were like trained to have
45-minute blocks
of focus where someone sat us down and
made us do stuff
and then did that for years and then
even through college
especially if you're like a quote
unquote good student um
you kind of played by those
institutional rules and then you're set
into
an economic context uh where
it's completely different and so i just
want to note the meta issue here
which is that and you brought it into
the room which is that like
you know the conditions of schooling and
the conditions of work
uh for many people are completely
different these days
um and the schools have not caught up
right so to prepare you to be
working for yourself in this kind of
like gig
economy kind of like entrepreneurial um
kind of post-post-modern service
industry like there's
a crazy diverse economic landscape in
which
there's nothing like uh
the routines and schedules and
disciplines of schooling
to be found so so there's a certain
thing that i call the habit body
right and the habit body is literally
the the way you
sit and the movements you make with your
hands when you talk
and the disposition to get up and get a
drink and the disposition to go to the
bathroom at certain times
so it's like really this embodied habit
uh set and
it kind of like down propagates from
the other more explicit cognitive and
more
reflective cognitive functions into the
body
so the first place that with these
because this is an issue of habit body
which is that you've built up
over many years uh a certain disposition
towards
extrinsic motivation in institutional
contexts
right which is what you said like if
there's no deadline it won't get done
and i'm not super interested in it
because if i was super interested in it
then
i would do it so it's also extrinsically
motivated there are certain things in
your life which you're not mentioning
which you do
probably really well and really
effectively um
on a pretty consistent basis because
they're things that either you need to
do
or the things that you're super
passionate about
that you can't not do some of them could
be friendships
uh they could be other aspects
so the first recommendation is actually
to
think at the level of the habit body and
so this is about
actually changing
the nature of your physical routine
like changing the nature of chairs
changing the nature of bedtimes and
wake-up times
uh changing the nature of meditation
postures or
thus rhythms and disciplines of work
so some people find it necessary to
actually
get like a little studio or someplace
that they can go to rent a simple room
to do their work in because they need to
commute
and leave their space of living
so and i'm not going to prescribe one to
you because i don't know
your habit body so instead of thinking
of it like something you need to do in
the realm of
thinking and cognitive operations and
like script rewriting or something
i think about it at some of you need to
do at the level of
changing embodied
so that's the first one and the second
one that
uh you know that and this moves up
out of the out of the body into into the
more mental realm but you know
motivation is very tricky
motivation is not in the domain of
development and
it's actually not in the domain of the
transcendent either because in the
transcendent everything's perfect
already
basically always already so a lot of
what we consider to be motivation
is in this realm of the realm of
installment
and i think this was mentioned in the
last
one or basically that you
you have to hit on the deepest
aspects of character and personality
before you can do any real skill
development and capacity development and
productivity and work
so most of the time what i see in like
attention deficit disorder
and kids who are underperforming in
school and these kinds of things is
mostly is that
you know they're actually pretty
reflective on the context that they're
in
and they have pretty good reasons for
not giving a [ __ ]
about the assignments so there's this
deep question of how can we attach
the dynamics of insolvent to the
capacity development and productivity
that happens in
development so that's like the trick and
how to attach the intrinsically
motivating
work to that work which
quote unquote needs to be done by which
institution you're in or
the need to make money and things of
that nature uh
so that's the second bit you know work
in the habit body that's good change
that that helps a lot
and then think about the
think about what you're really doing
with your time
and the degree to which it resonates
with
the images uh
and imaginable landscapes that actually
characterize
who you think you are um
and uh that is
a difficult question to ask under some
socioeconomic conditions because
there's actually a duplicity or split
itself
between the deepest image
and longings of
the soul and the conditions of material
embodiment development capacity
and institutionalized context um
so yeah so that's at another level this
is kind of like saying
you need to figure out what you're
really passionate about what you really
want to do
and then you'll do it if you can get the
habit body
set um but even if your habit body is
really well locked in
and you're not clear exactly what your
quote-unquote dharma is
uh you know what your unique gift
to give is then there will always be
these fluctuations
of of motivation
and that cascades down into the
inability to focus and
pay attention and specifically to
prioritize correctly
prioritizing is ultimately an exercise
in values
and um until you know
who you are and what the image is that
you're actualizing
it's hard to know exactly what is most
important
and valuable in the moment so so work on
the habit body work on the
clarification of self clarification of
self image
those would be my two recommendations
and
uh and then just pick one
like pick one of the the uh
you know to-do list and just iterate
with it and see how it works
um that would be my my other
recommendation if you can find someone
to hold you accountable
that also helps like if you have a
friend you can be like dude
call me today in the afternoon uh and
make sure i've done this
uh that kind of stuff which you would
also you get in school and you would get
in a normal work environment it's like
someone looking over your shoulder and
be like hey bro did you do that
so that helps too if you can find
someone to bring into
a kind of system of accountability
all right hopefully that was helpful to
to you and
it showed a little bit of the
applicability of the metapsychology
moving between
installment and development i didn't
really touch transcendence but you can
imagine the loop
but this dynamic between image of self
folding into capacity development and
capacity actualization which is to say
production productivity that's a very
important
move to be able to make and to be able
to step out of oh it's not
i'm not capable i'm not efficient i'm
not productive like
maybe is not the actual issue it's not
an issue of skill it's not an issue of
becoming
more attuned and adept with operating on
what you're operating on
the issue is actually in the domain of
insole and it's an issue of clarifying
the image of what you are and
who you're doing excuse me what you are
and why you're doing what you're doing
so
that can clarify a lot
all right thank you more questions
thank you auntie so man you had a
question that i i'll read for her
considering pre-tragic tragic and
post-tragic
how do compounded iterations of the
cycle
play out in your framework um
yeah so this is a deep question
because stations
are different than stages so
there are compounding iterations
within the pre-tragic tragic
post-tragic and there are basically
movements in life that have you cycling
through those stages repeatedly
so unlike when you're moving up stages
of hierarchical complexity
like you move up to a higher stage and
you solidify the capacity to work there
and if basically the context remains
relatively the same you're going to be
able to just operate
at that level repeatedly
there are these enduring stage
acquisitions which in my model under
development
are in the place of capacity so that
language cognition capacity capacity is
like
just there but stations
don't um stations don't have that same
dynamic
stations need to be repeatedly
kind of moved through and this notion of
the compounding is i think important
so most people um
in early childhood if
like you are lucky and for many because
this is the case
you are pretty tragic developmentally
appropriately
pretty tragic like you're a child um
you know this makes sense and it's
usually at some point in late
adolescence when you're moving to
resolve the adolescent identity
crisis that you have the opportunity
to confront tragedy now many people get
tragedy
much much earlier and the human uh
psyche can adapt to that and many
remarkable people
in fact emerge precisely because
uh of early tragedy they emerge
profoundly
uh remarkable capacity of people but the
the kind of
modal course is one where in late
adolescence this is when you have your
first confrontations with real profound
limitation death illness
failure evil things of that nature
and so resolving your relationship to
that can take a very long time and
usually
once you've seen it then you can start
to be
detecting tragedy in many many places
and you can actually metabolize a
tragedy that you've witnessed or
experienced in your own life
and move in a proper sense into a
post-tragic relationship
to that kind of tragedy right okay i get
family members dying as a tragedy like
and i can actually now be at these
funerals and feel the full
intensity of the sorrow but also feel
myself
uh able to make meaning of it
and be someone have an image of who i am
in tragedy that i can bear right you you
know you've hit a tragedy
when you there's an unbearable image of
self when the identity structure
itself cannot maintain uh
and so most people experience this with
breakdown like uncontrollable tears
uh things like you know overwhelming
uh depression to the point of almost
like a catatonic state where you can't
move sort of the freeze response
so you know you've had a tragedy proper
when you have that kind of
reaction because what's happened is that
the who you are
the image of self uh has been lifted up
into a context that
is completely inhospitable to that match
right um and so you have to there's this
forced evolution of the image of self
and
the post tragic occurs when you have
you have kind of like seen through the
unbearable image
into a new image of self where now the
self can
be in the tragedy without being
destroyed by the tragedy
and uh so so you can do that in a domain
of tragedy
like i said like losing beloved family
members and then now you have this
ability
to be with people who've lost family
members right um
and you have an ability to uh you know
be moved to your core by it but not be
shattered by it to the extent that um
you are like i said incapacitated by the
nature of the tragedy
and almost can't take responsibility for
your actions like
in the context of real tragedy when
you're living a tragedy it's happening
like in the moment right now
you are often relieved from normal
responsibility because you're in a
tragedy like if your mom dies
you're like hey guys i can't go to work
next week my mom died
right so like you're you're in it and so
one of the dangers of
moving out of the pre-tragic into the
tragic and getting stuck in the tragic
is that you can have an identity
structure and this is sometimes pointed
to it like
as like the victim mentality you can
have an identity structure that itself
is
fueled off of residing in strategy and
being freed from quote unquote normal
responsibility because you're in
tragedy right so that
again phase specific there are moments
in life when yes
you're in a tragedy you are relieved
from normal responsibility
but you need to then find a way to
evolve the image of
self so that it's not destroyed by the
tragic context but then can actually
sometimes thrive in the context of
tragedy
so but the point i'm making is that you
can run that in one domain of life
or at one level like um
you know sometimes it just happens in
like dogs dying or
legs being broken or college is not
getting into
it's the first thing that breaks the
bubble of the pre-tragic
and you engage tragedy and then you
become post-trad
in a kind of limited set of contexts
but then the bigger tragedy occurs or a
tragedy of
a kind you couldn't even imagine before
occurs
or you become aware of the existential
human tragedy at scale right
and so what that means is that now you
need to run that same operation you just
did
hopefully in this where you were like in
a safe practice
container limited tragedy
you can run that exercise you did to
engage now the more
the larger tragedy um
and uh and then again the unbearable
image of
the unbearable image of self the
shattering of that image
and then the reconstituting of the image
and
and that will happen again and again and
again throughout life
so it's not that like you become
post-tragic and like boom
you're post-tragic forever it's like no
you just had practice doing that
run of the stations you're going to get
more practice
you need to become good at doing that
run of the stations
uh rather than thinking that if you
solve the problem of tragedy
once you've solved it everywhere that's
the wrong mentality that's like the way
a developmentalist thinks about it it's
not true
you actually need to get used to the
general process of
running the stations and so just think
about like if you experience profound
tragedy like in your 30s
but then you have this family and you're
with these people now for 30 40 more
years and you deepen the love
relationship with these people
and then like your wife dies or your
child dies
completely different than the tragedy of
your parents dying when you were 30
right so much more profound and it needs
to be more profound because you've
become and sold with these people you've
gone down and into these
lower relationships so that's the other
thing to get is that
the deeper the ensoment the deeper the
tragedy
like the more you love the more it hurts
when the person dies
now if you've had experience running the
stations then you can actually
use that more profound depth of
dramaticity
to catalyze even greater evolution of
image of self
right so there's this like very profound
dynamic of like
risking total heartbreak
in the process of installment and that's
kind of like the fuel that
drives the evolution of character um
so yes this was a good question
um and there's more to say uh about that
and then of course there are other
stadiums as well
which we can come to
thank you manu for the question thanks
zach so another question by
dorial uh please don't meet your
secretary
hey zach thank you um my question is
what's your take on the state of
psychotherapy and
what types of therapy are most
supportive of installment
and kind of how does therapy play a role
in supporting transcendence
if at all totally good question
um so it's a few things one is that
you know there was a shift and i'm not
sure
precisely when to date it but it's
definitely
in full swing by the 90s away
from extended
depth psychological treatment modalities
and towards truncated
cognitive behavioral and eventually
psychopharmaceutical
treatment modalities and so that's worth
noting which is that
had we been having this conversation in
like the 60s or 70s
i it would be completely different
conversation first of all few many many
fewer people were pursuing
things like quote unquote therapy and
the main modalities that were
popular like gestalt therapy rogerian
therapy
classical psychoanalysis jungian
analysis those things
had never been even associated with or
even potentially watered down by things
like cognitive behavioral therapy
and um forms of psychiatric care
basically administered
by um
you know large uh
for-profit uh healthcare
agencies that's the first thing which is
that the context in which one
now pursues therapeutic modalities
is one that has changed radically in the
past 30 years and i think the quality of
care that has been administered
has decreased
even as it has increased in quantity the
number of people being treated
for psychiatric and psychotherapeutic
conditions has increased but the quality
of treatments come down so that's the
first thing to mention which is that
i'd love to say like go singing go see a
jungian it's like a therapist
you know but to do that you need to be
basically independently wealthy and be
lucky enough to live in a place where
some of these guys work if you're not
independently welfare and you have
health insurance
then you actually are limited to those
people
within your uh network
and most of them will incentivize the
briefest briefest duration treatment
and also incentivize those treatments
that end up sending you towards
psychiatric medications
so there's been a medicalization
and a biologicalization of
psychotherapy so that's just worth
putting out there
so that's also like a word of caution
which is that if you are deep in
an insolvent process which is to say
that you're likely experiencing
intensities of emotion such as
depression
anxiety difficulty sleeping intense
dream life incursion on waking life
interpersonal difficulties things of
that nature if you're experiencing
those and you go to
a mainstream psychotherapist you could
easily be routed into
taking uh psychiatric medications
that's the main thing that will happen
to you
so uh and i could give a whole long talk
about
the dangers of that um the iatrogenic
plague actually that's sweeping through
the country
now more so after the pandemic
of secondary and third order
physiological and psychological effects
from psychiatric medications
so first thing is
if you're tackling issues of installment
you're going to have intense emotional
dynamics
if you bring some of those to the wrong
people they'll try to put you on meds
which is worth noting so if you bring
them to the right people
then you need to be thinking about a few
things
if you're doing therapy for installment
now the thing worth mentioning is that
all three of these modalities are in
every exchange every interaction all the
time
so you need to
think about at least a few things when
you're
seeking someone as a
sometime called this psychopump right
this is the traditional word an alchemy
like a
a soul guide
which is what the therapist ought to be
so the first one is shared world view
shared framework shared sense of what
the psyche is so this would be in the
domain of
development cognition thinking what is
this therapist working model
of the mind
does this therapist for example believe
depression as a result
of a you know
messed up neurochemistry or
is this therapist actually open to the
idea that depression could be
a legitimate move through
phases and stations of emotion right
that's just an example so and then
another thing is like is this
therapist how what are they politically
right like would i agree with their
political views um
do they have strong enough political
views that when i'm voicing something
that actually bring politics in
like that's a little weird so like you
need to ask a lot of questions of the
therapist
to figure out if you would actually
trust yourself to their guidance and
that's all stuff in like the cognitive
domain
um in the domain of
insolent uh you you need to think is
this
cognitive behavioral therapy which they
intend to give me tools or i walk away
in 20 minutes and i just take care of
myself
or is this someone who's looking for an
open engagement of working with
my living images of self right and so
that would mean
more longer term conversations where
they're open-ended and you can do dream
work
and you can do free association work and
actually
dig into the psyche rather than just fix
it as quickly as possible with drugs or
cognitive behavioral therapy
and then the transcendent bit and where
therapists can help with transcendence
you know i'm not sure that they should
like uh i think there needs to be
a division of labor uh to some extent
in the you know kind of working with the
elements of the
of the psyche and you know
many therapists will have had training
in mindfulness practice and they'll know
the usefulness of like dialectical
behavioral therapy which is kind of like
a zen
inspired approach um
but to actually get transcendent
extraction of symbolic immortality um
uh you know there's kind of like
it may be better to actually keep
therapy as over there helping me kind of
adjust to the world and the domains of
development and kind of like clarify the
images of self
um but not seeking the kind of quote
unquote religious
from the therapist um but rather seeking
the religious
from the religious um and uh
and vice versa which is to say don't
seek therapy
from a zen priest right they don't know
they know how to meditate they don't
know how to
give you psychotherapy and do dream work
and
think about like whether you need to go
back to graduate school or something
it's like that's not there that's not
their uh domain so that sense of like
and this goes back to wilder's sense of
what an integral
psychotherapy approach would be it's
like you need to
kind of come in and you need to look at
a whole bunch of things and it may be
that you learn karate from this guy and
meditation from that guy and you do
learn cognitive behavioral therapy
from this therapist and then you have
instead of an actual therapist like a
coach or an elder or someone else who
helps you clarify
your image itself so
so that's a little bit on there so both
a word of caution
and noting that uh yeah picking the
right person is something that
takes that takes time and figuring out
if you're
is it that i need uh you know
deep dream and image work and to process
trauma and move through uh tragedy
or is it actually that i'm seeking the
transcendent which
which you're not going to get from
therapy which you need to find a way to
actually be in touch with a living
tradition of symbolic immortality
so thank you good question hopefully
that was helpful
thank you toriel so the question from
ron that i'll read for him what light
might the model shed on the current
burning issue
of individual inner work versus
collective action
the idea on one hand that one should get
their own house in order
before trying to change the world versus
the belief that collective action is too
urgent to wait for us to do individual
yeah excellent excellent question um
so i've said a couple times i think i
said it today too
that when you when you run the i'll just
call the axiom2 rotation
for those of you who know landry's
metaphysics when you when you run this
rotation from the imminent
uh excuse me from installment to
development to transcendent and then
back again to installment
there's this moment there at the with
the transcendent
when you actually through choice create
the conditions
of your installment for the next loop
um and so uh
there it's kind of a false divide that's
positive in the question
and but it's ubiquitous in the culture
which is that
like there is a choice not to act
um that you're you're always actually
creating the conditions of your
installment through every choice that
you
make so the notion of
the separation of work on self from work
on the world
i think is in a sense a little bit part
of the struggle that we're in um
so uh and once that's said it's like oh
yeah
of course and so i'm not like i'm not
saying this is like uh
like an insight here but the the you
know what it is is a very
slight refrain of the question which is
how can one responsibly act
on the world while acting
with one's own while acting upon oneself
because the the basic truth of the
psyche is that
um you know the
what am i trying to say
so if you
if you believe that you are
complete and correct
uh and then you act from that
place um you are
in a sense and this is what i meant by
like the truth of the psyche
in a sense you're moving against the
dynamic
of the psyche which is one as we've been
pointing out of
transformation evolution
growth right phases stations
stages none of these are static all
parts of the psyche
are moving evolving changing
so in a sense it's like the
stance of profound epistemological
humility
uh and then a profound kind of
losing face in the domain of
insolent and then a profound
sense of one's own continuity with the
rest of the world through symbolic
immortality
that all of these three domains to
actually be engaged
means you're engaging the world like
you're you're not going to clean up your
own room
by staying in your room
there's a way that one must actually
you know use uh use the world
uh as the alchemical vessel
in which one evolves the psyche
so so moving beyond that split and this
is one of the problems if you if you
just meditate or you just do
psychotherapeutic work or you
just study um uh
it's easy to actually have that fiction
that i'm removed from the world
but if you try to weave all those
together
right if you try to actually in a
multi-modal way
get that axiom to rotation moving
you're going to end up falling
deeper into the world now it may not
look like
activism as people know activism and i
think that might be the actual question
but it's going to look like engagement
in the world
so so yeah so but if the question is
should one participate in social
media and in political
action campaigns uh as they are covered
by
social media and the news media um
my responsibility like maybe maybe not
uh you know um
so that would be the that would be the
thing yeah
it's not it's not clear to me at all
that
um what counts as political action
and often what counts as quote unquote
working on the problems of the world
it's not only clear to me that those uh
those things should be
undertaken by the people who are
undertaking them and so that's maybe
more directly to your question
which is that it's easy to get into
situation especially in the dynamics of
installment and especially in
contemporary cultural contexts
it's easy to get into a situation of
reifying the pre-tragic or
prolonging and complicating the tragic
uh by engaging in a lot of the kind of
post-modern late capitalist forms of
identity
politics and protests so that's worth
noting as well that
uh some of those dynamics are uh
unhealthy now they're not any more or
less unhealthy than the other things in
our culture
like being obsessed with professional
sports or uh
overt materialism uh and ladder climbing
careerism um so these things are
you know equally as pathological as what
you're seeing in
uh kind of uh protest culture
uh so that's a little bit more there may
be more directly to the question
but if but if you're actually doing the
dynamic of the metapsychologies i'm
describing it
then you're definitely in the world
working on the world working with the
world being transformed by the world
whether that's visible eligible
as political action or something is
it's not clear
we're on for the question so anita
had a question would you like to meet
yourself
hi zach i heard you mentioned last week
that you worked with a body worker to
help you navigate yourself
through your installment stations
i was wondering what your thoughts are
regarding the physical body in
relationship to the three modalities of
the psyche
especially the insolvent embodiment
interface i'm a body worker
and i often sense
a deep connection and a deep innate
intelligence with the physical body and
its efforts to communicate with us
i wondered what your thoughts were on
that
totally excellent question this is also
an area where i haven't done
systematic thinking so i'm going to try
my my best here but
so it seems clear that
all three modalities which would say
development in psalm
transcendence that all three of them
leave something like
signatures within the physiology
so the most obvious ones and you
mentioned it in the domain of
installment
when you're looking at the way the image
of self
is actually written onto the biology of
the body
in gesture and habit body as i mentioned
so real wilhemree called this the the
armoring
or the characterological armoring where
you actually kind of
wear your habitual emotional
habit body you end up wearing it
in your in your physical form uh
so that that's one place where
the nature of movement practice
and body work and as i was mentioning
thinking reflectively about transforming
your own habit body which is like
changing the nature of your
physiological armory that kind of
came down from character structure uh
that's all how that looks in the domain
of
basically installment
the transcendent however is where
the basically
body itself if i can say that
lives like in
development and capacity building you're
using your body
in ensoment you're actually
have created an imaginal
image of your body like hillman writes
about this
the alchemists write about it too they
called it the imaginal
ship of death which is to say you
actually get out of your physical body
you live in an imaginal image of your
body
but in the transcendent that's when you
return to the actual
blood and guts body and that's
it's in the transcendent in the dome in
the domains of
the symbolic immortality of being matter
the symbolic immortality of being life
right that i am continuous through my
breathing
and through the rhythm of my heart
with all other living being things that
takes place
before all awareness before all
consciousness at the level of the
transcendent in the actual
body so a lot of body work practice
and yoga and meditation and things
actually work on that dimension of the
body where it's actually
locating awareness and consciousness
in the body as the body which is hugely
important and massively curative
uh and related to that notion of
changing the habit
body and the character structure the
armoring and the reichen sense
um and then it would be in the domain of
development where you actually get a lot
of mouth like this is where you can get
the body used as an instrument where you
get self-instrumentalization
for the sake of capacity um
and uh so in installment if you're
depressed you're gonna have depressive
gestures and
if you have an image of yourself that's
you know triumphant you'll
walk with your chest puffed out and
stuff like that in development it's more
like if you're
a physical laborer or a mathematician
or a you know mother
or a um you know finance guy
you're gonna have different uh physio
physio physio physiological
signatures of the capacities you've
developed
so different than the image of self and
the image of body and different from the
body as
such is the body as
instrument tool um so think about an
athlete's body or a musician's
hands right that their changed and
strengthened
um as a result of the active
capacity development um so
and again it's like remember all three
of them are being heuristically
differentiated
but in every psychic event all three
occur
so like when the athlete's exercising
the athletes exercising the image of
self
making choice through the transcendent
and also building capacity
so it's just that uh yes a body's always
always involved
um and i think you know
a lot of what i'm seeing when i work
as a psychologist i read gesture and
habit body and i'm curious about
you know the way the image of who they
are they're wearing
and then about the kind of forms of
gesture
and forms of posture and other things
that signal to me capacity
has been acquired and then also just
like
where is their awareness and
consciousness are they even
can they rest as the
right body as aware of the body as such
you can detect those things
almost by watching someone uh and
listening to them speak for a little
while
you can tell how much is their body
being used as an instrument or a
particular capacity
how much has their body been basically
like
you know shaped by this image of self
and then how much are they actually
aware of their body as that they are a
body
it can be as their body so that's my
first pass
um i'm not sure if any of that is
correct but we will
have to see as i think more about how
embodiment
basically it's like embodiments to the
category that applies across all three
modalities
basically is what i'm saying um and so
it might be helpful to think about
embodiment from those three perspectives
and different signatures you're seeing
in the body
and things that the body does and
proclivities of the body is being
related to those three somehow
rather than vitamin being in like one of
the three
so
conor you had a question
yeah exactly this is great um so i was
wondering what
advice would you have for enriching a
new
installment station or just for
transitioning from transcendence
to installment like what practices would
you recommend if any
especially if after a phase transition
um
through transcendence the perception of
next and soulman station
somehow feels unviable or like too big
uh and then like related what potential
pitfalls are likely to cause a skip
of insolent um going out of the proper
axiom two sequence
uh directly from transcendence to
development in our era
assuming that's even possible or common
well that was a great question i was
excited
to hear my own terminology used back at
me uh
yeah so you said a couple things that i
want to pull out because i think they're
interesting and very
um important because it's a general
thing so you mentioned that
through certain dynamics that took place
in phase shifts in the transcendent
you were then thrown back into a
position of insolent where the image of
self you are trying to
integrate was too big or seemed not
feasible is that right did i get that
right
yeah right exactly and this is
and this is super common like this is
one of the main
things that one finds when you look at
research
in uh psychedelics and meditation and
specifically meditation traditions that
are like empowerment traditions
uh is that the
kind of download as it were from the
transcendent
and the kind of dynamics of symbolic
immortality that got
cooked in samadhi or satori or
ayahuasca or something ended up landing
you back in the world quote unquote
uh with a for lack of a better phrase
grandiose image of self
all right um and uh
and so that's one of the things that i
think
is so powerful about
the dynamics of symbolic immortality is
that
they actually do reposition the
potentialities for new
basically stations of installment so
this is your question and it's like i've
been empowered through some transcendent
experience and now i feel like i'm at
the doorway
of certain stations of installment that
are like
like whoa i didn't sign up for this
[Laughter]
like this seems like a much bigger uh
couple things i have to go through so
so that's when i'm gonna pull out and
see two a little bit and i think that
this is a very
uh important question because i think
many people
experience this and it doesn't only
necessarily come from
meditative experiences or drug
experiences or something
if you behave a certain way create a
certain artifact
make certain choices you can end up
putting yourself in a position where
you're at the beginning of a path
of installment that seems way steeper
and
way bigger than you ever thought so
totally love it and this is like one of
the things we need to learn to work with
this is what religion used to give us
was both the empowerment
and the humility to start at
station one instead of
coming out being re-empowered having the
vision of the new self that's possible
and imagining you're already there right
so that's the first thing to note which
is that
if you're if you're through transcendent
insight
have the door open to a new set of
stations for installment
uh you need to figure out where your
first
step is right and that's often usually
something more like a massive
humbling or a uh
like a dark knight of the soul kind of
thing right
so you come out and you're in the
equivalent of that uh
fusion with the symbolic immortality
right so this is the equivalent of the
pre-tragic where there's no
there doesn't seem to be any split
between you and this
imaginal image of a future world
in which you're the self is now like
co-located with all of these incredible
things
so you're kind of fused with the image
the first step is getting out of fusion
into separation distance criticism
of that new image so this is like the
tragic where all of a sudden there's an
interruption
to that simple thing so this is the
first thing you need to do is figure out
how to get
distance from that modality of symbolic
immortality
to criticize it uh only after that
and probably traversing quite a lot
can you move into some form of sweetness
or reintegration with that image which
has been
refined and put through
the kind of fire of realism and
criticism
so that's kind of the modality it's like
you first come out and you're like holy
cow like i just got told that i need
to be this person xyz that means that i
already kind of aim this person
xyz and then you need to be like no
you're not
you're not that person you could be
right what is
the kind of like ecstatic ordeal
that one needs to go through to
transform to be able to become that
person or to become some version of that
which has been refined through that
through that ordeal
so so it's not so much saying like
you know yeah all that shit's [ __ ]
and you're now you're just a grandiose
personality and if you do
ayahuasca too much you'll just become a
narcissist and a selfish person that
you know that can't happen but it's also
that you've just placed before yourself
a tremendous kind of
journey of learning and transformation
so as opposed to having kind of like
accomplished it
by symbolizing the immortality you've
actually just started it
is the idea and the images of
self-remember are created by the soul so
the images of self that you're pulling
out of that symbolic immortality
uh you know does not necessarily need to
be something you can accomplish in this
life
right like the soul pulls images from
deep
um so uh it's worth noting that
as you separate from that
form of symbolic immortality and bring
the
new image itself in line with existing
conditions you may realize that yeah
this is actually a
a soul image that is
operating across uh
across dimensionalities rather than
being a specific earthly request
so i'm getting a little bit out there
but this comes from steiner and
other traditions that actually grapple
with this dynamic of transcendence and
insolent um
and what you find there again and this
is again the risk of
certain forms of psychedelics is that
you're pulling down images
from other realms man like and then to
think that they're actually relevant
here on this earth and this time
that's where you can get the grandiose
personality stuff it's not that they're
not real
it's that the soul's plugged in across
uh multiple lifetimes
so all right now i'm getting out there
into some
ontologically treacherous water so
so yeah so that's me kind of like
theorizing into that space i think it's
a wonderful
question so the basic answer is like
yeah totally you are that person
but you need to get yourself into a
situation to take that first step
out of the the unity into the separation
criticism
work so burn that image in the fire and
then
see what comes out on the other side
thank you so we have another question
from ben
do you want to meet yourself
thanks i'm not sure whether this is a
how-to question or do you have further
examples but
um something like so you know working
with oneself or in oneself or
with others in small groups how do you
recognize okay well um you know
the modality which we should be working
with here is
um which one and how how to move between
modalities
and as an extension to that um
in in dyads or in small groups um
what is the dynamic or is there a
dynamic you know
could for example one person be
working in one modality and the other
working in a different modality how do
you how do you see that
or is there necessarily a congruence
this is exciting man i'm loving this
because it's like i've not just thought
this stuff through and so you guys are
giving me my own vocabulary back to me
and so i'm having ideas which i've not
had before so one of them is that it's
definitely the case that
there are personality types or character
structures that orient to
one of the three modalities right so
that you could get a group of people
where it's like oh that guy's handling
the language and the cognition capacity
she's handling the installment
and you know she's handling the
transcendence like you could get a group
like that where you actually get a
division of labor
and the personality type for lack of a
better phrase
or rather the archetypal kind of image
of that person has them constellating
around that so i think
i think there's something true in there
now
you have to take that with a grain of
salt because clearly
the culture and the institutions and the
schools
and other things are tipping the balance
in favor of
some people being some ways as opposed
to others
so i think there's a as we talked about
last time with the question
we've skewed heavily towards the
linguistic and the cognitive
um to the extent that when we move in
the domains of the transcendent
and insolent we become either fetishized
or
traumatized and et cetera so i think one
of the things we're looking for and this
gets the other part of your question
diagnostically
one of the things we're looking for is
where
are people leaning from i'm back to like
the
language of gesture so a lot of what you
end up
seeing is uh the
basically malformation of uh
expression um because of cultural and
societal impulse
so you have to actually disengage
i'm getting like very diagnostic now as
like a psychotherapist would disengage
from the content of what someone is
saying
right if you're trying to figure out
okay this person's hurting this person's
coming to me they're seeking help
right i want to be able to give them
advice
about whether they need to work on these
issues of installment or they need to
actually
build some cognitive apparatus and skill
capacity or if they need to actually
meditate and
uh you know get a spiritual teacher or
something so what i would do is i would
say
disengage from the content of what
they're telling you
and listen to literally the
relationship between the emotion of
their voice
and that content and the gestures and
habits of their body while they're
speaking
and that content so what you're looking
for specifically is
the uh the cue towards
symbolic language imagistic language
or cognitive language right
and then the emotional resonance that
each of those
has right like um
when people describe to you their
problem or if they describe to you even
their
life and the situations that they're in
there will be a waiting towards those
kinds of languages
all right there will be a waiting
towards either cognitive language spoken
with
emotional distance or imagistic language
spoken
with emotional intensity or symbolic
transcendent language again probably
spoken with emotional distance
right so that's just an example but
let's say someone
is trying to explain to you their life
but it's really too actual complicated
for them to explain to you so they're
trying to use cognitive language and now
they're getting
really emotional trying to use cognitive
language makes you think they actually
don't understand what the hell is going
on in their life
um or they're describing to you an image
like of their professional job and who
they're going to become and they sound
completely not
enthusiastic all right so who cares what
their what the image is
the fact that they're describing an
image of their future self
and they're not enthusiastic at all
means that they probably need to do some
work in the domain of installment
to clarify the image of self right
so that's just two examples of like what
you're looking for it's like which
modality are they like
speaking from an in and then what's the
tone and
resonance of their body and their
emotion as they're speaking this way
and you know i find this to be very very
useful um
and if someone is for example speaking
in a very emotional way about something
that
could just be a description from a
cognitive perspective
like their relationships and their
family and things of that nature
sometimes you need to invite them into
imogistic language
right ask them to give you a metaphor
or an image that encapsulates this thing
they're trying to describe cognitively
and see if they can do that or not
sometimes that alone will be massively
helpful
sometimes actually helping people do
that to move
from the linguistic and cognitive into
the imagistic
can be very helpful and similarly if
someone is
overwhelmed by image and they keep uh
essentially you know describing these
scenes these like poignant heartbreaking
scenes from their life
which they can't metabolize
you can help them by getting them to
speak symbolically
right you can help them with the
symbolic immortality construction
get them to see you know that this is a
dynamic involving
mothers and motherhood or
suffering and nothingness
or whatever the thing is that's so deep
that they can't resolve the image
right so moving helping people move
between the modalities is very useful
therapeutic modality and also gives you
a sense of
which modality you then get the most
help in right
like i said sometimes if people are
overwhelmed by the complexity of their
life
they'll switch out of trying to
understand it and they'll give it to you
in some simple metaphor
and you're like okay that's a that's a
too easy image
uh can we shift from the image to
language
tell me more tell me a lot more oh
you're actually confused about what's
going on
you need work in building social skills
and reflection techniques and things of
that nature
so so that's a little bit of like
freestyling into the nature of that
question
which is a very good one but uh
you know i haven't had enough experience
myself or with other
practitioners clinicians to really know
how it would hash out in terms of these
kinds of
practices so that's that's work that
needs to be done but that was an initial
first pass so hopefully that was
illuminating a little bit
okay so we have a question from bonita
and i'll read it for her
so do you have any um
would you be able to recommend any
authors or literature artists or
teachers whose work is primarily focused
on the post tragic
huh
and the one that came to mind first was
the classic you know victor
frankel right man search for meaning i
think is one of the one of the more
classic
post-tragic texts um
you know the truth is that
most mature literature
and philosophy is post-tragic
this is one of the things that some of
the qualities that
we're actually honing in on when we call
something mature
or sophisticated um that doesn't
necessarily mean that it is
really developed hierarchically complex
right you can actually get very simple
artistic
products poetry and other things um
uh mary oliver i think is an example of
post-tragic many people read her as
pre-tragic
but if you know anything about her life
you actually realize that mary oliver's
is post-tragic um and it's not because
it's
um complicate complicated and
hierarchically complex from a
developmental perspective
in fact it's quite the opposite um and
uh she's actually
working in the realm of image in a
post-tragic way and really getting
symbolic mortality out of her
relationship with nature and things of
that
quality um you know i
uh so yeah so and then when it comes to
philosophers in particular
uh you know you have to look at
well it's actually easier to identify
pre-tragic or tragic philosophies um you
know analytical philosophy
which denies the reality of the ethical
would be something like pre-tragic
right because like if you're not even
admitting that the ethical is a
legitimate category
of discourse then you can't even embrace
tragedy
as an actual thing in the world
so those forms of analytical philosophy
that deny the reality of ethics
are pre-tragic some forms of post-modern
theorizing are
tragic and actually stuck in the tragic
which is to say there's a kind of
complicated
grief that's taken place in which the
identity structure itself gets connected
to the identification and
uh kind of witnessing of the tragic
without an attempt to resolve it
in fact uh a kind of fetishization
of the tragic um a lot of post-modernism
is like that
uh actually uh and then so yeah the
post-tragic forms of philosophy tend to
be those ones that
grapple with the ethical and the
existential explicitly
and which deal in
the limits and nature of the tragic
without
getting stuck in it um and
you can find those from all periods of
history so it's not like the
our meta modern period has a uh
you know kind of like special access to
the post tragic not at all
there's you know again the stations are
not stages so we've been cycling through
the pre-tragic tragic post-tragic
for a very long time so you can find
post-tragic work from
from all historical epochs uh
so hopefully that's that's helpful
all right fantastic um pradeep had a
question
we asked a while back yeah thanks
nicholas
zach could you comment on the different
practices that
you found to be very helpful in
your own process or with people you've
worked with i know you have mentioned
dream work and bodywork and
expanded on bodywork earlier but there's
a there seems to be a collection
and is there a way to think about these
i mean well a few things one is
you can you can use the metapsychology
to
organize a taxonomy of
psychotechnologies all right so you
could say
looking at the existing
psychotechnologies therapeutic
modalities meditation techniques
pedagogical approaches etc you know
which of them go where um which is to
say
like uh you know vipassana meditation
christian contemplative prayer zen
buddhism these things probably go in the
transcendent
and union constructive imagination
and freudian dream work and some forms
of
like internal family systems therapy
work would go in the installment
and then many traditional forms of
education
cognitive behavioral therapy things of
that nature go in
development so that's the first thing
that it gives us is an opportunity to
see okay
we can organize the different
psychotechnologies into these three
categories
and then if we go back to the prior
question and think about diagnostics
and we can figure out which type
of psychotechnology would this person
probably benefit from
then we can start to have this kind of
like integral
toolbox that we can pull from um
and so the first thing that needs to be
done there is actually
some kind of curational enterprise
where we bring together under those
largest uh aspects of the taxonomy we
bring together kind of like best in
class
of all of these different modalities and
i i haven't done that
you know i have only taken on those
modalities
that have kind of come across my path
and that have been
been necessary and helpful for me and
haven't had an opportunity to actually
through systematic research and vetting
do a comprehensive curation
but i would love to see that kind of
work done that work was begun
actually under the auspices of a
different
metapsychology when ken wilbur was
booting integral
uh institute there was an attempt to
basically
build a comprehensive taxonomy of
psychotechnologies based on integral
theory
so that's the first thing i'll say it's
like there's a lot of those
and the few ones that i could endorse
like could actually bias you all against
exploring the full range of space
um and i don't want to do that but i
will say a few things i mentioned last
time
a specific uh form of crying practice
that i used and a specific form of
body work and moving practice that i
used and then
meditation and contemplative prayer
techniques which i use
and that in conjunction with
probably way too much time looking at
books
and text and engaging in
way too abstract and complex like
discourse with people
so those those combined um
the
so you're looking for like are you
actually personally curious about what
i've done
or was that enough of an answer i mean
uh yeah i mean that's enough of finance
if you want to share anything more
it's fine mike my question was only
because transcendence and development is
quite clear there are a lot of things
but and soulman seems to be this piece
where
it's not really clear what is the
spectrum of practices
that are available yeah so there are
many many practices available in
installment at least as many as there
are
in development and uh transcendence so
the ones that i've engaged with are of
course
dreamwork dreamwork being a classic one
uh and there are particular forms of
dreamwork and
the ones that i've seen hillman use
specifically in his book dream in the
underworld and then
in from image excuse me from type to
image
that stuff's the best that i've seen
where you work with the dream
not to extract the symbol into the
transcendent but you work with the dream
as an
image and work the uniqueness of the
image to clarify the uniqueness of your
own
self so dreamwork is classic
constructive imagination in the jungian
sense is also
good this needs to be coupled with a
strong transcendent meditation practice
because it works like completely
stilling the mind
and then kicking off through some kind
of generator function
thought literally something like a
waking dream so the constructive
imagination exercises
are done consciously and intentionally
to induce
a free-form imagination so that you can
witness
spontaneously the constructions of your
own unconscious and
if you're a serious meditator sometimes
these things will happen
automatically by accident and you'll get
this like
vision of bodhisattvas or that kind of
stuff so
but it is possible to cultivate and jung
did this completely outside of like
explosive meditation context he would
sit and he would play with blocks
literally like stones and little rocks
and build little towers and things
and that would free his cognitive mind
and he would get these then images that
would just flood into his awareness
including images that were prophetic
about the coming of world war ii and a
few other things
so if you again some people walk or ride
bikes
or sex but whatever happens that it
frees
from cognition and opens the
not like you're daydreaming and making
it something happen
like you're fantasizing about something
and i'm gonna get that and then
but you it's your mind by itself
endogenously creating
image that's what you want to create so
that's active imagination
uh and then um practices that engage
with
the imagery that's possible through
language
in in the non-cognitive function so
poetry
uh music
and those
those forms of engagement so for me
music i was a musician before i was
anything else
music was was huge uh so
so that's a little bit more in the
domains of installment but there's
there's more than that like the
vajrayana tradition of buddhism
i would count under the realm of
insolent where they actually have these
specific practices
of constructive imagination where you
in your imagination get the image of the
deity
and then meditate on the properties of
the deity and then flip it so that you
are wearing the mask of the deity and
you become the deity and are empowered
through the mandala of imagination that
you've created over prior meditations
so vajrayana buddhism is another example
christian contemplative prayer similarly
if you work with free-flowing images of
christ and things of that nature
so beautiful thank you
so one more question that i gotta wrap
but this has been blast guys thank you
all right we have one more question uh
david
swedlow go ahead
yeah thanks um zach i'm i'm curious i'm
i'm really loving the way that you're
exploring this as you're bringing the
model of the meta psychology out to us
and
any really engaging the questions as you
said the reflections are helping you
look at it differently
um and i'm curious as well about the
sense of um
whether you see the model in some way as
a coping mechanism your deeper model of
the way of understanding
and something like that the work of the
wounded healer is to bring the model out
to people
so that it can be challenged more deeply
so that it gets
it gets tested in the fires of actual
experience of other people
and so i'm curious as you're engaging in
this process and then doing it do you
get
insights in yourself about
you know kind of a deeper sense not just
the insides of the model but inside
onto how you came to the model or how
how this is growing you does that make
sense
totally i mean this is uh this is why
uh i love teaching
because like you don't really know
anything until you've tried to
convey it to someone and uh and then
being in that exchange like this q a
here made me wish i did the whole thing
q and a but i couldn't because i
actually had to lay out the framework to
make this q a useful but
so yeah there was it was it was very
exciting this session for me in
particular
um because it made me realize hey people
are actually understanding this
because it seems like wow would anyone
even be interested or understand but you
guys are giving back to me
expressions in my own terminology which
are more sophisticated than some of the
ones that i uttered so i'm like yes
people get it and are actively
constructing with it
and then two is that yeah there was a
sense i have
of fulfillment and being able to teach
this way and it'll feel even better once
i get the book out on this
um which is to say
this metapsychology and my
personal quest to basically metabolize
my life experience which has been so
intense over these past years as i
shared in the last session
to to make that as fruitful as possible
to the world and it feels like i never
would have been able to bring the
metapsychology forward had i not been
through that
cauldron of intensive soulmate um
so yeah i'm feeling a sense of rightness
that feels
good like to the point of having the
capacity and development
you need to actually actualize an image
of self that you were given
is what it feels like is beginning to
congeal so
i'm super kind of grateful for the
opportunity
to do that here on the stove with y'all
and
i am getting all of these uh transcribed
and then we'll be working up that
transcript in
either essay or book form but uh
don't give me any due dates because
that'll work with due dates so we'll see
when it
when it yeah when it comes but uh but
yeah thank you again
everyone i'm kind of honored to to have
had this opportunity
but turn back around so i can see you
all again and say goodbye
so thank you so much zack uh on behalf
of everyone at the store
for this deeply rich and eye-opening
series
that you put together we've got some
demands for an ask zach series so i
don't know if that's on the table
for you ask
i think so i think so like because i'm
judging
uh but i'll need a couple weeks off
sure all right guys thank you thank you
um i'd also like to plug in a stowe
session beginning in 30 minutes
post that in the chat uh the pandemic of
group think young and the collective
shadow with uber boyo
that's in 30 minutes you can check the
link in the chat
um so thank you everybody and i will see
you soon
[Music]
hey